<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Robert Diab</title>
    <link>https://robertdiab.ca/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Robert Diab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 08:38:23 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://robertdiab.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Police bodycam use about to rise in Canada</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/posts/uptake-police-bodycams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 08:38:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/posts/uptake-police-bodycams/</guid>
      <description>After years of reluctance by police and government in Canada to embrace bodycams, Colin Freeze reports that things are beginning to change.
His informative piece (behind a paywall at the Globe) notes a series of changes on the ground across Canada in the wake of George Floyd&amp;rsquo;s murder, captured on video last summer.
Soon after that occurred, Trudeau announced $50 million in funding for RCMP bodycams. Ontario has recently announced $70 million in funding, with two of the province&amp;rsquo;s largest forces &amp;ndash; Peel and Toronto &amp;ndash; budgeting $10 and $34 million respectively for body-worn cameras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/about/</guid>
      <description>I teach and practice law in British Columbia.
I work in the Faculty of Law at Thompson Rivers University and with the criminal defence firm Jensen Law in Kamloops, BC.
I write journalism and scholarship on a range of topics, from law and technology to civil liberties and human rights.
I co-edit of the Canadian Journal of Comparative and Contemporary Law, and hold a PhD in law from the University of British Columbia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full publication list</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/full-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/full-list/</guid>
      <description>Books: The Harbinger Theory: How the Post-9/11 Emergency Became Permanent and the Case for Reform (Oxford University Press: New York, 2015)
Guantanamo North: Terrorism and the Administration of Justice in Canada (Fernwood Publishing: Halifax, 2008)
Book Chapters: &amp;ldquo;The Demise of Rights as Trumps&amp;rdquo;, in Ben Goold and Liora Lazarus, eds, Security and Human Rights, 2nd edition (Oxford: Hart Publishing, 2019).
&amp;ldquo;Counter-terror Law: Canada&amp;rdquo; in Kent Roach, ed., Comparative Counter Terror Law (Cambridge University Press, 2015)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/research/</guid>
      <description>A full list of publications can be found here
“Search Engines and Global Takedown Orders:
Google v Equustek and the Future of Free Speech Online”
56 Osgoode Hall Law Journal (2019)
“The Road Not Taken:
Missing Powers to Compel Decryption in Bill C-59, Ticking-Bombs,
and the Future of the Encryption Debate”
57:1 Alberta Law Review 267 (2019)
“Does the State Have a Compelling Interest in
Searching Device Data at the Border?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/writing/</guid>
      <description>“The Great Unread: On William Deresiewicz’s ‘The Death of the Artist’”
Los Angeles Review of Books (13 October 2020)
“This One Country (Not America) Should Enshrine Police Body Cameras into Law”
The National Interest (22 June 2020)
“B.C.’s problems with money laundering run so deep they’ll be hard to resolve in the short term”
The Vancouver Sun (30 January 2020)
“Compelling people to reveal their passwords is posing a challenge to police and courts”</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
