<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Robert Diab</title>
    <link>https://www.robertdiab.ca/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Robert Diab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://www.robertdiab.ca/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Full publication list</title>
      <link>https://www.robertdiab.ca/full-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertdiab.ca/full-list/</guid>
      <description>Books: The Harbinger Theory: How the Post-9/11 Emergency Became Permanent and the Case for Reform (Oxford University Press: New York, 2015)
Guantanamo North: Terrorism and the Administration of Justice in Canada (Fernwood Publishing: Halifax, 2008)
Book Chapters: &amp;ldquo;The Demise of Rights as Trumps&amp;rdquo;, in Ben Goold and Liora Lazarus, eds, Security and Human Rights, 2nd edition (Oxford: Hart Publishing, 2019).
&amp;ldquo;Counter-terror Law: Canada&amp;rdquo; in Kent Roach, ed., Comparative Counter Terror Law (Cambridge University Press, 2015)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://www.robertdiab.ca/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertdiab.ca/research/</guid>
      <description>Internet governance “Search Engines and Global Takedown Orders:
Google v Equustek and the Future of Free Speech Online”
56 Osgoode Hall Law Journal (2019)
Encryption and digital privacy “The Road Not Taken: Missing Powers to Compel Decryption in Bill C-59, Ticking-Bombs, and the Future of the Encryption Debate”
57:1 Alberta Law Review 267 (2019)
“Does the State Have a Compelling Interest in Searching Device Data at the Border? Emerging Approaches to Reasonable Search in Canada and the United States” Oxford University Comparative Law Forum 1 (2018)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Diab</title>
      <link>https://www.robertdiab.ca/posts/bio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertdiab.ca/posts/bio/</guid>
      <description>I am an associate professor in the Faculty of Law at Thompson Rivers University in Kamloops, British Columbia, and a practicing lawyer.
I write about a range of issues in law and technology. Some of them can be found here in shorter essays and scholarship on topics that include internet governance, compelled decryption, and digital privacy.
I have also written about national security, human rights, and civil liberties. (A full list of publications is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>https://www.robertdiab.ca/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertdiab.ca/writing/</guid>
      <description>Content creation “The Great Unread: On William Deresiewicz’s ‘The Death of the Artist’”
Los Angeles Review of Books (Oct, 2020)
&amp;ldquo;Should We Be Forced to See More Canadian Content on TikTok and YouTube?&amp;rdquo;
The Conversation (June 2021)
Democratic decay “The Big Fail: The Internet Hasn’t Helped Democracy”
The National Post (Oct 2018)
Compelled decryption “Compelling people to reveal their passwords is posing a challenge to police and courts”
Salon.com (May 2019)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
