

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Categories on Robert Diab</title>
    <link>https://robertdiab.ca/categories/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Categories on Robert Diab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://robertdiab.ca/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Police bodycam use about to rise in Canada</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/posts/uptake-police-bodycams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 08:38:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/posts/uptake-police-bodycams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of reluctance by police and government in Canada to embrace bodycams, Colin Freeze reports that things are beginning to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His informative &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-police-are-increasingly-sold-on-bodycam-technology/&#34;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; (behind a paywall at the Globe) notes a series of changes on the ground across Canada in the wake of George Floyd&amp;rsquo;s murder, captured on video last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after that occurred, Trudeau announced $50 million in funding for RCMP bodycams. Ontario has recently announced $70 million in funding, with two of the province&amp;rsquo;s largest forces &amp;ndash; Peel and Toronto &amp;ndash; budgeting $10 and $34 million respectively for body-worn cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Freeze points out, Canada lacks law regulating the use of bodycams, giving rise to a host of issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police forces that do have them must create their own policies on when video can be released. In cases of videotaped deaths and injuries, the decision will lie with provincial watchdog bodies such as Ontario’s Special Investigative Unit – which currently take months to investigate before releasing any findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3623440&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; forthcoming in &lt;em&gt;Criminal Law Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;, with Marshall Putnam, calling for &lt;em&gt;Criminal Code&lt;/em&gt; amendments that would guide police and prosecutors in the use of camera evidence &amp;ndash; when to record, disclosure, privacy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without codifying rules in federal law, camera uptake and use in Canada will be a confusing patchwork of law and practice, with unfair, inefficient outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
