<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>scholarship on robertdiab.ca</title>
    <link>https://robertdiab.ca/categories/scholarship/</link>
    <description>Recent content in scholarship on robertdiab.ca</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://robertdiab.ca/categories/scholarship/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Posner on what law profs should be doing</title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/blog/archives/2023/12/29/thoughts-on-posner-on-what-law-profs-should-be-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/blog/archives/2023/12/29/thoughts-on-posner-on-what-law-profs-should-be-doing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Orin Kerr has circulated on Twitter a &lt;a href=&#34;https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1291&amp;amp;context=journal_articles&#34;&gt;3-page piece&lt;/a&gt; by Richard Posner from 2007 that captures the essence of an idea at the heart of a debate unfolding in recent years over what it is that law profs should be doing in their capacity as scholars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posner does a great job defining a highly contested normative conception. Is he right that it should still play a central role in what we do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 1960s, he says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law professors used to identify primarily with the legal profession and secondarily with the university. …Law professors in that earlier era were hired after a few years of practice, on the basis of evidence (heavily weighted by performance as a law student) of possessing superlative skills of legal analysis. A law professor was expected to be a superb lawyer and to see his primary role as instructing generations of law students so that they would become good, and some of them superb, lawyers — instructing them by precept but also by example, by being a role model; and the role was that of a practicing lawyer. The scholarship that law professors did tended to be either pedagogical, as in the editing of casebooks, or to be of service to the practicing bar and the judiciary, as in the writing of legal treatises, articles on points of law, and contributions to legal reform, exemplified by the American Law Institute&amp;rsquo;s restatements of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the late 60s, the model was challenged from two directions: law profs drawing on the social sciences (mainly economics) to help “articulate concrete social goals” and profs (mostly on the left) critical of law on “political grounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legal academy began to drift away from the world of lawyers and judges. More of the writing and teaching in law schools was based on “insights of other fields, such as economics, philosophy, and history” and overtly more political. The “traditional model” came to seem “narrow and stale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But an older generation kept it alive. And so they should have, says Posner, since “[e]ven at the most intellectually ambitious of the modem law schools, a large majority of students will become and remain practicing lawyers; and there is a good deal more to the practice of law than economics, or philosophy, or feminism, or theories of race.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet he also says that skills like reading a case, acquiring a “bag of rhetorical tricks”, professional judgment, etc., aren’t all the modern lawyer needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “first-rate” legal education should be more expansive, since “the law has become too deeply interfused with the methods and insights of other fields”. Students should be schooled in “statistics, math, science, and technology” — and “maybe only a third” of the time spent at the best schools should be doctrinal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even to do this well, he thinks law schools should be hiring profs that are good at doing a certain kind of work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The messy work product of the judges and legislators requires a good deal of tidying up, of synthesis, analysis, restatement, and critique. These are intellectually demanding tasks, requiring vast knowledge and the ability (not only brains and knowledge and judgment, but also Sitzfleisch) to organize dispersed, fragmentary, prolix, and rebarbative materials. These are tasks that lack the theoretical breadth or ambition of scholarship in more typically academic fields. Yet they are of inestimable importance to the legal system and of greater social value than much esoteric interdisciplinary legal scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Posner right?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who work in a law faculty debate the merits of Posner’s position almost daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consciously place ourselves somewhere along a spectrum, but mostly closer to either end. On one side, the doctrinalists — dealing mainly with the “messy work product” of cases and statutes, hope to lend clarity and direction to lawmakers and lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the other end are those steeped in the social sciences or the humanities, talking mainly to other profs and scholars. Each looks askance at the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with Posner that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i. a good portion of what needs to be taught in law school is doctrinal and practical, since a good portion of law students (not necessarily a majority) need to acquire this knowledge if they’re going to be good lawyers — regardless of whether they’re going to be appellate barristers or small town solicitors; and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ii. you can’t do this well as a teacher without having spent time as a scholar in the traditional model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To expand on point ii, if you haven’t done a modicum of doctrinal scholarship — grappled with the “messy work product” of courts and legislatures in some area, it would be hard or unlikely to convey a solid foundation in an area or an effective bird&amp;rsquo;s-eye view. This is a completely impressionistic assertion on my part. Maybe it would be more accurate to say: you have more to work with as a teacher of practical, black-letter courses if you’ve published in the area than not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Posner’s point is more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sees that law and society have become too complicated to exclude the insights of the social sciences and other disciplines. Notably, he thinks these other forms of “law and…” scholarship should take &lt;em&gt;up over half the curriculum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posner’s point, then, is that we should hold on to the traditional model, but make ample room in law schools for teaching and scholarship of another kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the kind done by what are, in effect, tenured lawyers, law clerks or legislative librarians (nothing wrong with them, of course!). But a kind that would do justice to our position in the academy — a place that makes possible forms of work and study that can’t be done elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The contrary view: &amp;lsquo;he’s such a phoney!’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some say that when law profs stray into the social sciences, philosophy, economics, they’re out of their depth. They become at best pseudo-academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a PhD in these other disciplines — just a PhD in law, or not even! — what gives them the authority, the legitimacy to waltz into the fields of philosophy or economics, pretending to be someone they’re not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short answer: nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in many case, scholars who do “law and X” aren’t purporting to do philosophy, economics, history, per se, but something &lt;em&gt;primarily&lt;/em&gt; grounded in law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a difference, in other words, between borrowing methods, concepts, or tools from these other disciplines and aiming to dwell &lt;em&gt;primarily&lt;/em&gt; in those spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the difference between a piece written &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; law scholars that happens to be informed by methods and terms from economics or sociology, and a piece written primarily &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; economists, etc. In the first case, the primary aim is to shed light on ‘law’ in the broadest sense, rather than ‘society’ in the broadest sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a work like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/dignity-of-legislation/081E97115D1536F3F8F85363FE3102C7#:~:text=Jeremy%20Waldron%20here%20attempts%20to,a%20respectable%20source%20of%20law&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dignity of Legislation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is Jeremy Waldron doing political philosophy or something in law called ‘constitutional theory’? In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Between-Truth-Power-Constructions-Informational/dp/0190246693&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Between Truth and Power&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is Julie Cohen doing &amp;lsquo;social theory of technology&amp;rsquo; or law?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meeting in the middle?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate about the legitimacy of “law and…” might then come down to perceptions about the legitimacy of drawing on other disciplines you have a tenuous grounding in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I concede this is a tough thing to assess, and makes the task of peer review in many cases more challenging. But I’m not sure it makes “law and…” work illegitimate per se, or scholars committed to this not worthy of being considered members of the club in good standing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question at the end of the day is not whether a scholar doing ‘law and X’ is really a phoney economist, philosopher, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s whether they’ve raised new questions about law or shed light on it in some new way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that even if it’s only at best debatable whether they have done so, they have succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
